There are several ways in which standardised
working methods benefit the workplace, which
include reduced waste, increased productivity,
increased customer satisfaction, and compliance.
In this video, we'll look at
each of these in more detail.
Let's start with reduced waste.
There are a few areas within the working
environment where waste can be reduced
through standardized working methods.
Firstly, standardised working methods can
help ensure that resources are optimised.
What does this mean?
By using standardised procedures, the amount of
resources can be measured, thus minimising waste.
We've previously looked at just in time
ordering for keeping inventory lean.
Having a standardised process ensures that
only what's needed is ordered, which prevents
additional inventory and overspending.
Such processes also help to minimise errors.
By following set guidelines, employees
are less likely to make errors, thus
reducing the likelihood of rework and
wasting time, materials, and money.
Increased productivity, set guidelines,
as we've just seen can be very important.
It's important that these are clear, well
defined, and employees can follow them.
When done correctly, guidelines help employees
to carry out their tasks efficiently.
It minimises thinking time and helps
to ensure tasks are completed to
the correct standard every time.
It's easy to see how such systems can reduce
variations and maintain consistency across output.
Customer Satisfaction Consistency, as we've
just looked at, ensures that products are
produced to the same standard time after time.
This builds trust for the customer who know
that they can rely on good quality every time.
Not only is product quality
reliable, but so is time.
We've already seen that standardised
working methods reduce time, and this
also ensures that customers will get
their product when they expect it.
Meeting customer expectations in this
way ensures that trust is built up, and
the customer is consistently satisfied
with the product and service, resulting
in repeat business and positive reviews.
Compliance.
In Unit 1 we saw how important legislation,
procedures and processes are to businesses.
Often, an industry will need to comply
with certain regulations to ensure that
they remain safe and offer good quality.
Think of an electrician, they must be
qualified to carry out electrical work
and work to set safety guidelines.
When this is not done, organisations
face heavy fines and they are
unlikely to get repeat business.
Standardised processes help an organisation
to identify potential risks and ensure
that the necessary controls are in
place to manage them effectively.